בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is דף צדי, daf Tzadi,
but we pick up at the משנה mishna on the bottom of
פ"ט עמוד ב', Peit-tes amud beis, and we are, actually no, we
read that משנה, mishna, we read the גמרא gemara on it, right?
So we're two lines from the bottom, thank you, on פ"ט עמוד
ב', Peit-tes amud beis, and we're talking about back to the question
about minimum sizes you need to be חייב chayav for carrying. That
is certainly a very dominant theme in this section of the מסכת.
masechet. So, two lines again from the bottom: תבלין כדי לתבל ביצה
קלה. Tavlin kidei letaveil beitza kalla. Spices enough to add to a
like a light egg, which רש"י Rashi says is a hen egg,
like a fried scrambled hen's egg, so enough spices to add some
a little salt and pepper for that and that's enough to be
חייב. chayav. So ורמינהו, v'raminhu, I'll ask you on this: תבלין שנים
בג' שמות ממין אחד או משלושה מינים אסורים ומצטרפים זה עם זה.
Tavlin shnayim b'gimmel shemos mimin echad o mishlosha minim assurim umitztarfin zeh
im zeh. If you have various spices, two or three different names,
meaning different types of... well, what the question is different names means.
So I'll just tell you first what רש"י Rashi says. רש"י Rashi
says it means like white pepper, black pepper, and so on, that's
different names, and ממין אחד mimin echad is they're all peppers. Or
from three different מינים, minim, you have, I don't know, pepper and
salt and cinnamon and so on. תוספות Tosfos has a very long
discussion here in תוספות Tosfos because תוספות Tosfos says that actually משם
אחד, mishem echad, let me just read you the key line in
תוספות, Tosfos, he says like
this: דג' מיני איסור כגון ערלה כלאי הכרם ושל אשר
ושל עיר הנדחת קרי ג' שמות.
dgimmel minei issur k'gon orlah kilayim kerem
v'shel
asher v'shel ir
nidachas kari gimmel shemos. That
there are times when the גמרא gemara says name like what it
says, why do you get מלקות? malkus? You get מלקות malkus because
of משם זה לא השם המביא לידי מלקות, mishem zeh lo hashem
hameivi lidei malkus,
and שם shem means the nature of the איסור. issur. So תוספות
Tosfos actually reads this and this gets him into a very side
discussion, which isn't our topic, but you should be aware of it,
that he reads that if you have let's say spices of three
different types, you have a little from spices of עבודה זרה, avoda
zara, and you have a little spices of ערלה, orlah, and you
have a little spices of כלאיים, kilayim, and you combine them all
together and you eat a כזית k'zayis worth, you get מלקות. malkus.
Now, מלקות malkus for what? You didn't do a minimum amount of
any one of those. So that becomes this question of is there
some type of like a generic לאו lav that you would combine
of all different types of forbidden foods that you could be חייב
chayav if you even combined of different categories? And normally it seems
not, but that's why there's this long discussion in תוספות. Tosfos. So
he suggests to read it that even of different prohibitions would combine,
but we're going to bracket that for now. The point is that
different types of spices, same spices, different spices, they all combine, אסורים
ומצטרפים זה עם זה, assurim umitztarfin zeh im zeh,
and presumably it means they combine to give you a minimum amount.
It also means that they combine that if you have different types
of spices within let's say a stew and because of the combination
of them you're able to taste it, but with only one of
them you couldn't taste it, nevertheless, because they combined you taste, that's
considered like it's still present and it's not בטל. batel. Okay fine,
so that spices combine. ואמר חזקיה, V'amar Chizkiya, now חזקיה Chizkiya says,
במיני מתיקה שנו הואיל וראויין למתק קדירה, biminin metika shanu hoil v'reuyin
l'mateik k'deirah,
that only when they are all of similar that they all are
like sweet spices, not as some salty and some sweet and some
savory and so on. Only then that they combine
because then they can all do a similar function of sweetening the
pot. But presumably if they're sort of different, like you have a
little bit of vinegar and a little bit of, what's a sweet
spice? I don't know, sugar! Sugar! And a little bit of and
cinnamon maybe is sweet, I don't know, and a little bit of
garlic. So if they don't all, I mean, you know, if you
have enough of any one it's a problem, but they don't all
combine because they don't somehow work together. So therefore, that would not
be a problem that it would be considered like it gives taste
into the pot and that it's forbidden. So if that's true, only
those types of things combine. So גמרא gemara says, הא לאו הכי
לא? ha lav hachi lo? So if they're different types of spices,
they don't combine? So how come our משנה mishna says that different
types of spices that you would put in the egg all combine
to a minimum amount if they don't really work together? So the
גמרא gemara says: הכא נמי חזו למתק. hacha nami chazu l'mateik. Hereto
we're talking about that they're all the similar types of spices, they
all have a similar function of sweetness, they're not of different types
and therefore not that they work in, you know, in different directions.
Now I do want to mention, I mean, this is a very
curious גמרא gemara two ways: number one, תוספות Tosfos asks an obvious
question, if you look at the top of צדי עמוד א' Tzadi
amud aleph here, תוספות: Tosfos: הואיל וראויין למתק קדירה, hoil v'reuyin l'mateik
k'deirah,
תוספות Tosfos says, הואיל וממתיקין הוי ליה למימר. hoil u'mamtikin havei lei
l'meimar.
It should say not that they in theory could sweeten it, but
that they actually are fine. But then he says: ואם תאמר היכי
מיירי אי בנותן טעם. v'im tomar heichi mayri ei b'nosin taam. If
because of the combination, a little sugar, a little salt, a little
vinegar, a little cinnamon, there's some taste that's discernible of these spices,
again we're talking about spices that are forbidden, that's the original context
not our case of שבת, Shabbos, so אפילו שאר מינים... afillu shaar
minim... Who cares if they're all sweetening? At least now you can
taste them. ואין בהם נותן טעם, ve'ein bahem nosein ta'am, if they
can't be tasted, אפילו מינים מתוקים נמי, afilu minim metukin nami, so
then who cares if they're all sweetening? So he says ויש לומר
דאפילו ve'yeish lomar d'afillu יש בהם נותן טעם, yeish bahem nosein ta'am,
שרי בשאר מינים דנותן טעם לפגמו. shari beshar minim denosein ta'am l'pgamo.
If they're not doing the same thing, some are sweetening and some
are this, some are that, then even if they're tasted, they're not
being able, they're not doing a positive taste because they're not working
together. Okay, which is a little funny. That should also sort of
depend on the context. It could be another explanation also is, and
this is a whole discussion about when things have to give a
taste in order to make a mixture forbidden, do they have to
give over their distinct taste? Like if you have sometimes because you
have a little vinegar and a little this and a little this
and a little this, it affects the taste of the entire thing,
but you can't taste the vinegar. It's the combination that changes the
taste, but it's not you can distinguish the particular taste of the
thing. And that might be the way to understand what this is
saying, is that if they're all sweetening, and they all add a
sweetness, so even if you can't detect the different sweetness of the
cinnamon as opposed to the sweetness of the sugar as opposed to
the sweetness of the honey, but you can detect sweetness, that's enough,
that's like you're tasting then. But if they're working in different directions,
it's not enough to identify the type of taste that they particularly
are giving. Anyway, that's in terms of the issue of making the
mixture forbidden. In terms of the relevance for שבת, Shabbos, it's also
quite strange. You will remember, maybe, that when we talked about this
idea of צירוף, tziruf, combining different things, we said, for example, that
you could combine food of a camel with food of a sheep,
and different types of foods as long as it was going by
the largest of the sizes. And we never asked the question of
but no one animal will eat a little bit of all of
those things together. It became a formal rule that once it's this
amount, you can combine different things that all are defined by the
same amount, even if this hybrid combination is not meaningful. Here, the
גמרא Gemara wants to say that the combination of the various spices
actually work together. So it's interesting why here the גמרא Gemara is
insisting on that, and it did not insist on that elsewhere. And
also, again, why do they have to be sweet? If I like
a little onion and a little salt and a little ketchup on
my eggs
and I have the
minute, so why shouldn't that be enough? Unless again, the point is
yeah, but it's not enough of any one of them, which seems
to be what's bothering the גמרא. Gemara. So again, what's interesting is
that the גמרא Gemara normally, at least in the past what we've
seen is, it doesn't matter that if this hybrid combination is usable
or not, as long as in a formal way they all go
by the same size. Here, the גמרא Gemara is making a reasonable
assertion that they have to be functioning together, they have to work
together as a combination. But again, it is interesting why it's demanding
it here and not elsewhere. Okay, so now we
continue. קליפי אגוזים וקליפי רמונים, Klipei egozim ve'klipei rimonim, סטיס ופואה, stis
v'puah, כדי לצבוע בגד קטן. kdei litzbo'a beged katan. So the shells
of nuts, the shells of pomegranates, and these various other plants which
are obviously made for dyes, enough in order to use to make
a dye that you would use to dye a
small piece of a cloth that you would put at the opening
of a hairnet. So now let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
ורמינהו, u'reminhu, I'll ask you on that.
המוציא סממנים שרויים, Hamotzi samamanim shruyim, if you take out actually dyes
that have been steeped in water, that have been actually not just
the plant, but they've been converted to dye, so how much dye
are you חייב chayav for? כדי לצבוע בהן דוגמא לאירה, Kdei litzbo'a
bahen dugma l'irah, enough to
use to dye to color a little sample that you would put
on the warp of the loom. So that's obviously smaller than this
amount for the hairnet. So how come there it says this small
amount, the size of a sample cloth, and here it's enough to
put it for the opening of a hairnet? So אמר רב נחמן
אמר רבה בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, לפי
שאין אדם טורח לשרות סממנים לצבוע בהן דוגמא לאירה. lefi she'ein adam
tore'ach lishros samamanim litzbo'a bahen dugma l'irah. We said this once before,
an earlier גמרא Gemara brought all of these contradictions together and the
basic answer was that it's different when it's pre-processed or post-processed. If
you've already turned it into the dye, the liquid, then even a
little bit is significant. You'll take a little bit of that liquid
to color even one sample. But if you're taking out the actual
plants and you haven't processed it yet for dye, you're not going
to bother to do the process unless you have a more substantial
amount. So here we're talking about taking out the plants, you need
a more
substantial amount, otherwise it doesn't have significance. Okay, so those are the
various plants that are used for dyeing. מי רגלים, Mei raglayim, urine,
which presumably they would use urine and other types of things for
a type of a cleanser. So תנא, tana, we taught in the
ברייתא, Braisa, מי רגלים עד בן ארבעים
יום, mei raglayim ad ben arba'im yom, until forty days. What does
that mean, forty days? So תוספות Tosafos has a whole question. Does
this mean that it's only of an infant forty days old? Does
it mean
that the urine has only been around forty days? Starting forty days
it becomes effective, until forty days it becomes effective, and right, one
of those. All right, נתר
*Neter*.
Does it have to be פטור *patur* or is it?
Yeah, absolutely it doesn't have use. נתר *Neter* which is natron. So
תנא *Tanna*, נתר אלכסנדרית *Neter Alexandrit*, Alexandrian neter, which is again these
are types of things used as cleansers, ולא נתר אנטיפנטירן *velo neter
Antipantiron*, and not Antipantiron neter, which is some type of a thing
from the land of Israel which apparently was, I don't know, of
a different source I believe, of a plant source as opposed to
some other source. Yes. Type urine?
After that it's so and
that's so weird that you can carry it sounds like you can
carry gigantic amounts of urine.
Well again, I don't know how much. Maybe at a certain point
it would be useful for fertilizer. It doesn't just go by that
amount. Are there types some types of things that are considered completely
useless? Yeah, I mean the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* discussed that before, but
some types of things after a certain point maybe they're only useful
in other contexts and not in this context. But all of these
contexts the end of the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says that you use
it's measured by the amount that you would use to remove a
stain from a like to cleanse one of these small cloths that
you would use at the opening of a hairnet. So all of
these somehow were used in the process of cleansers. All right, so
בורית *borit*, which is we call בורית *borit* soap, but obviously some
cleanser. So let's see, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to ask what
בורית *borit* is. אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda: *Amar Rav Yehuda*,
זה חול *zeh khol*, that's a type of a sand. Funny, things
we would last think about using for cleansers, sand, urine, but anyway,
I mean they had some way of using them. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, והתניא *vehatanya*, didn't we teach in a ברייתא Braita,
*Braitah*, הבורית והחול *haborit vehakhol*, בורית *borit* and sand, so clearly בורית
*borit* is not sand. אלא מאי בורית *Ella mai borit*? So what's
בורית *borit*? כבריתא *Kavrita*. It is כבריתא *Kavrita*, which is רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says sulfur, גפרית *gafrit*. So מתיבי *meisivay*, I'll ask you on
this: הוסיפו להם *osifu lahem*, they added on the list of things
that are have a שביעית *shevi'is* status or שמיטה *shmitah* status, החלביצין
*hachalvitzin*, where they've no idea what it is, והלענין *vahale'inim*, which is
לענה *la'anah*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says which is some type of a
bitter plant, wormwood or something, והבורית *vehaborit*, and בורית *borit*, והאהל *veha'ohel*,
and אהל *ohel*, which is also some type of a cleanser.
They say
aloe.
They say aloe, we've discussed this before. I know that so here
the Artscroll said aloe, I think last time it was Steinsaltz that
said aloe, but I remember there was another גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that
made it sound very like the opposite of aloe. Aloe is very
moisturizing. Whatever it is, I remember we had this discussion last time
whether different types of aloe. Whatever it is, it's a different type
of a cleanser. Anyway, ואי סלקא דעתך כבריתא *ve'isalkatit kavrita*, if you
think that בורית *borit* is sulfur, כבריתא מי איתא בשביעית *kavrita mi
isa beshevi'is*? Why would sulfur have the laws of שמיטה *shmitah*? והתניא
*vehatanya*, we taught in the ברייתא *Braitah*, זה הכלל *zeh haklal*, this
is the rule, כל שיש לו עיקר יש לו שביעית *kol sheyesh
lo ikkar yesh lo shevi'is*, only something that has a root has
שביעית *shevi'is*, שאין לו עיקר אין לו שביעית *she'ein lo ikkar ein
lo shevi'is*, and if it doesn't have a root. And sulfur's what?
Sulfur's like a type of you mine it or something? Yes, it's
a type of a mineral. Right, so it's a mineral, so how
could שמיטה *shmitah* apply to sulfur? אלא מאי בורית *Ella mai borit*?
Fine, what's בורית *borit*? אהלא *Ahala*. It's this אהל *ohel*. והתניא הבורית
והאהלא *vehatanya haboris veha'ahala*, but we taught בורית *borit* and אהלא *ahala*?
תרי גווני אהלא *Trei gavni ahala*, there are two variations of it.
Okay. Like grease and sand? Yeah, but then you would have the
שמיטה *shmitah* problem because בורית *borit* has to be something that grows.
Okay. Anyway, so some type of a plant that is used in
the cleansing process. קימוליא
*Kimuliya*, which is another thing. So אמר רב amar Rav יהודה *Amar
Rav Yehuda*, שלוף דוץ *shlof dutz*, which means like stick and pull
out, some type of earth that is called שלוף דוץ *shlof dutz*,
a loose earth. אשלג *Ashlag*, what's that? אמר שמואל *Amar Shmuel*, שאלתינהו
לכל נחותי ימא *she'altinu lekhol nakhusei yama*,
I asked all those that went down to the sea, ואמרו לי
*ve'amru li*, שוננא *shunana*, that it's this thing called שוננא *shunana*, all
right, שמיה *shemei*, that's what it's called. ומשתכח בנקבא דמרגניתא *Umistakach binekva
demarganisa*, it's found in the hole of a pearl, of a pearl,
right, ומפיק לה ברמצא דפרזלא *umafik leh beramza deparzela*, and you remove
it with like an iron pick or something. So somehow it's some
type I don't know, maybe it means mother of pearl, I'm not
sure what it's supposed to be. But mother of pearl is actually
in the lid of the oyster, right, it's not in the hole
of the pearl itself. What is it, pearl dust? I have no
idea. Anyway, all those various things. Okay, and those are measured by
the amount of cleanser you would use to cleanse a garment, a
small garment. Okay. פלפלת כל שהוא pilpeles kol shehu, *Pilpeles kol shehu*,
the smallest amount of a pepper, ועיטרן כל שהוא kol shehu, *ve'itran
kol shehu*, the smallest amount of עיטרן itran, *itran*, which would also
which is some type of a tar, pitch, something like that, right.
מיני בשמים minei besamim, ומיני מתכות כל שהן *Minei besamim uminei matakhas
kol shehu*, the smallest amount of various fragrances or metal, we'll see
all what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* what all this is used for.
מאבני מזבח ומעפר מזבח *Me'avnei mizbe'ach ume'afar mizbe'ach*, מקק Makak ספרים sefarim
ומקק מטפחותיהם mitpachoteihem *makkak sefarim umakkak matpikoteihem*, if you have things that
now it goes into a different category, not things that are used,
but things that have to be put in a גניזה genizah. *genizah*.
So you have some of the stones of the altar of the
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*, funny that like that's referred to,
when was the last time anybody had stones of the altar of
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*? But okay. Or dust from
the altar, maybe some of the ground-up stones. the stones like got
rubbed against. מחק ספרים ומחק מטפחותיהם is like the dust that comes
from these books after like the moths have been to them, have
been at them, I mean. So it's like the waste product of
these actual, is there, I don't know, is there a word for
them? ספרי קודש, Sifrei Kodesh, like ספרי תורה, Sifrei Torah, right? You
know, well right, it's also like when things get brittle, you know,
and they sort of like start crumbling. But there's also, I think
the way רש"י Rashi explains it also means that this is like
the waste left over after the moths have eaten through it. Okay?
And מטפחותיהם are the things that you wrap around them, you know,
like the like the mantle and so on. Right? כל שהוא, kol
shehu all those, the smallest amount. Why? שמתניעין אותן לגנזן shematzninin osan
ligenzan because you put them aside in order to put them into
גניזה.
So even though you don't use it, you don't want it to
like, you know, you're not going to throw it out and even
the smallest amount is significant. You want to make sure that you
take the smallest amount and that you bury it. So רבי יהודה
אומר אף המוציא Rabbi Yehuda omer af hamotzi. ממשמשי עבודה זרה כל
שהוא. kol shehu? So
once we're saying that, even something that is forbidden because it's like
bad, even things that are used for appurtenances for idols, שנאמר ולא
ידבק בידך מאומה מן החרם, shene'emar velo yidbak beyadcha me'umah min hacherem,
you can't have even the tiniest bit, you have to destroy it.
So if it's significant because you have to destroy it, then therefore
even the smallest amount is something of significance, you have to do
something with it, you have to destroy it. Now the גמרא Gemara
before actually said explicitly that when the משנה Mishnah, said the only
thing you're חייב chayav on are things that people sort of that
are מצניעין כמהן, matzninin kamohen, which I mean that things that people
want to keep or you know want to set aside, was to
exclude things like איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah which you actually want to
get rid of. But here the interesting question, so as opposed to
the thing about the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, there you have no
use for it but you want to sort of you want to
protect it, you want to make sure that the right thing is
done with it and that it's buried. Here the small amount is
significant but because you want to get rid of it, you want
to destroy it. So does that give it significance in order to
say that even the smallest amount you've carried something of significance or
the opposite? Because the whole point is you don't want it, therefore
it has no significance and that was debated earlier. Here רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda is saying the side that it does have significance. Let's
first look now at these issues about what these various things are
before we get to the things that are buried.
פלפלת Pilpeles is not תבלין tavlin because otherwise it would have
been included in well maybe it's a special type of תבלין. tavlin.
So anyway let's see what גמרא Gemara. says. פלפלת כל שהוא, pilpeles
kol shehu, למאי חזי? lemai chazi? What do you use it for?
לריח הפה. lereiach hapeh.
Remember we discussed before about putting things in the mouth in order
or on the body in order to cover up bad smells. So
you would put this in your mouth to cover up your bad
breath. Now רש"י Rashi says in the משנה, Mishnah פלפלת כל שהוא
ואינו פלפל שלנו גמרא מפרש כל שהוא למאי חזי. pilpeles kol shehu
ve'eino pilpel shelanu Gemara mefaresh kol shehu lemai chazi.
So I don't know what he means. What's רש"י's Rashi פלפל? pilpel?
We had this discussion once before, right? Did they have black peppers
or did they have chili? Didn't we have this discussion? Which peppers
they had?
I believe black and white pepper.
They did not have our things? They just had peppercorns? They were
mainly from the New World. So when when רש"י Rashi claims that
the משנה's Mishnah. pepper is not the pepper his pepper, which is
the pepper in France, was there a different pepper in France than
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or did you anyway? Black pepper was
expensive because it's a tropical spice.
Yeah, it didn't grow in cold countries.
So they didn't have them? רש"י Rashi didn't have those peppers?
Only
through spice trade.
And there's also different colors of pepper, you know, peppercorn. Right.
I don't know what motivated רש"י Rashi to say אינו פלפל שלנו
eino pilpel shelanu unless רש"י Rashi figured that the peppers that they
had would nobody would use them to put in the mouth for
for you know for to cover up bad breath. But I'm trying
to figure like but none of these things, I mean I guess,
how could you put I don't know, could you put a little
bit of פלפלת כל שהוא, kolshehu would that have any effect on
bad breath? Like you can't smell one tiny bit of a peppercorn.
If it's crumbled it would become a כל שהוא kolshehu.
of a pepper. Yeah, I don't know. All right. I don't know.
Anyway, maybe different oil. I guess if you don't have toothpaste.
Yeah, well anything helps. But but really a כל שהוא? kolshehu. Anyway,
okay. עיטרן כל שהוא, itran kol shehu, the smallest amount of עיטרן,
so again which we said was like
tar. למאי חזיא? lemai chazya? What's it good for? לצייחוסא, letzichosa, which
רש"י Rashi says is a headache. Okay? So I don't know what
they would do. You'd put it on your head, on your temples?
I don't know. Anyway. מיני בשמים, minei besamim, various fragrances, Rashi says
all commentaries identify this term with a migraine headache, apparently tar was
used as a remedy due to its strong odor.
Oh, you would smell it.
Okay. Could be burning it.
Burning it. Okay, that's interesting.
It would be nauseous for a migraine, I don't know.
But I'm sure it would. All right. מיני בשמים, various fragrances, תנו
רבנן, tanu rabanan, again presumably because they would cover up smells of
the body and so on. Or המוציא ריח רע כל שהוא, hamotzi
reiach ra kol shehu, even something that smells bad. Now what do
you want something smelling bad for? So רש"י Rashi says that you
would use it also for some type of a treatment of sick
people. One explanation
רש"י Rashi says is that it would scare away the שדים, shedim,
the מזיקים. mazikim. So there you go. So anyway they would use
bad smells as well. שמן טוב כל שהוא, shemen tov kol shehu,
a little bit even a little bit of like nice oil, which
is you know the גמרא Gemara before said it was myrrh oil.
So again maybe even the smallest amount would be... ארגמן כלשהו, Argaman
kolshehu, which is royal purple, even the smallest amount. רש"י Rashi says
טעמא לא נתפרש. Ta'ama lo nishparash. Okay, and רש"י Rashi says maybe
they would also smell this. Okay. I don't know. וסולת הורד אחת,
u'besolat havered achat, one virgin rose, which רש"י Rashi says like means
just a young, a fresh leaf of a rose. But yeah, I
don't know if רש"י Rashi by leaf of a rose means a
rose petal, presumably he
does.
Yes, first virgin of the גמרא Gemara and a virgin rosebud is
a red embroidered decorative ornament that looks like a rose and is
known as a
עטילת
הורד, Atilat havered, עטילת הורד.
Atilat havered. Right. So yeah, so they bring that commentary down on
the side from the ערוך Aruch that it's some type of of
a of a colored garment. All right, but that's
a... מיני מתכות כלשהן, Minei matechot kolshen, the smallest amount of various
metals. למאי חזי, Lemai chazi, what would you use metals for? תניא
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר Tanya Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer שכן
ראוי לעשות ממנו דורבן קטן. sheken ra'ui la'asot mimenu dorban katan. You
can make it into a small prod of an animal, right? All
you need is a little bit of metal and you poke an
animal with it to get an animal moving, or maybe you could
make it into a needle. You know, a little bit of metal
can go a long way. Okay, so תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabanan, we taught האומר הרי עלי ברזל. ha'omer harei alai
barzel. Somebody takes, since we're talking about metals and amount of metals,
we talk about it in a different context. Somebody takes a vow
to give iron to the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash, How much iron
is considered the minimum amount? Not the minimum amount of significance like
for שבת Shabbos even the smallest amount, but the minimum amount implicit
if you're giving a vow to the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash. what
would we assume is the standard implicit amount that you're giving? So
אחרים אומרים, acherim omrim, other say לא יפחות מאמה על אמה. lo
yiphos me'amah al amah. So not less than a אמה amah by
a אמה, amah, like you know, a cubit by a cubit which
is a lot. Right? I mean, that's got to be a lot
of iron. I mean... Right, right, I mean it doesn't
say how thick it's supposed to be.
That is true, it does not say how thick it's supposed to
be, but still, you know, what is that? That's like one and
a half feet by one and a half feet or something like
that. Yeah, that's a lot. That's a lot of iron, I mean,
even if it's as, you know, unless it's like paper thin. Okay,
so למאי חזי, lemai chazi, what would they use it for? So
אמר רב יוסף amar Rav Yosef לכלה עורב, lechaleh oreiv, for the
for a chaser away of
ravens. Basically what they would do is that they would make spikes
like they would put up, you know, on the roof of the
בית המקדש, because you know, you got all of this wonderful burning
burning meat, it's going to attract birds, right? So you put them
up and רש"י Rashi says and you have like, you know, spikes
coming out of it and nails coming out of it and nails
coming off of the top. So it would be made for some
type of, you'd use it for a to chase away the ravens.
ואיכא דאמרי, Ve'ika d'amri, other say אחרים אומרים, acherim omrim, other say
לא יפחות מכלה עורב. lo yiphos mikaleh oreiv. It can't be smaller
than the size used for this כלה עורב. kaleh oreiv. וכמה, Vechamah,
and how big is that? אמר רב יוסף amar Rav Yosef אמה
על אמה. amah al amah. Same point except coming in it in
different directions. נחושת, Nechoshet, if somebody vows to give copper, לא יפחות
ממעה כסף, lo yiphos mima'ah kasef, no less than is the value
of a מעה כסף. ma'ah kasef. Now תוספות Tosafot actually asks, it's
quite funny because if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, לא יפחות ממעה
כסף lo yiphos mima'ah kasef he says תימה לרי דלא יפחות מפרוטה
הוה ליה למימר. teima l'Ri delo yiphos miproota hava lei lemeimar. The
smallest amount of the smallest copper coin was a
פרוטה. proota. כי היכי דתניא פרק כל המנחות, Ki heichi detanya perek
kol hamenachot, הרי עלי זהב, harei alai zahav, if you say a
gold, לא יפחות מדינר זהב. lo yiphos midinar zahav. So the minimum
is the smallest gold coins which is a gold דינר זהב. dinar
zahav. כסף, Kasef, לא יפחות מדינר כסף. lo yiphos midinar kasef. So
therefore if you say copper, it could be the smallest copper coin.
But why do we all of a sudden go to a very
different valuation of copper? And תוספות Tosafot doesn't really know, could be
of course that that's so small it's insignificant, but still it is
quite interesting. Okay, so that's copper.
We're not talking about a finished coin, we're talking about the raw
material.
Right, but תוספות Tosafot as well, when somebody said האומר הרי עלי
זהב ha'omer harei alai zahav and just vowed to give gold, the
minimum amount is the amount equal to you know, that gold coin.
So...
No, but we're talking here, we're talking about what is a useful
amount. Maybe you need a lot of copper.
Right, so that's what I said, it could be the amount of
one gold or silver דינר dinar can you do something with, the
amount of one פרוטה proota you can't do something with, right. So
yes, that could that could be exactly the difference. Okay, so תניא,
tanya, we turned the ברייתא, רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer לא
יפחות מצינורא קטנה של נחושת. lo yiphos metzinora ktana shel nechoshet. No,
by copper it's the amount to make a small little fork of
copper like a you know, like a you know, little, not little
your fork you would eat whatever at dinner with, but we'll see
what you do with it, a little implement. למאי חזי, Lemai chazi,
what would you use it for? אמר אביי amar Abaye שמחתכים בהן
את הפתילות ומקנחים את הנרות. shemechatkin bahen et hapitilot umekanchin et hanerot.
You use it to like make holes in the wicks and to
you know, scoop out from the from the lamps of the מנורה.
Menorah. So a tiny little like you know, a tiny little delicate
copper fork that you would use to clean out and to adjust
the wicks of the מנורה. Menorah. All right, so anyway, that was
just an aside of various various metals for the בית המקדש. But
for שבת, Shabbos, even the smallest amount. מקק ספרים ומקק מטפחות, Mekak
sefarim umekak mitpachot, so to the waste of you know, the the
the waste of the ספרים and of ספרי קודש Sifrei Kodesh and
of the wrapper things that you would the cloths you would wrap
around them. אמר רב amar Rav יהודה: So מקק דספרי, Makak desifrei,
מקק דספרי. Makak desifrei. Now we're going to give the list of
the different names of either the actual animals that eat away at
these various materials or like the waste product. רש"י Rashi, says that
it's the animals. So מקק is what you call the thing that
eats away at books, at things of parchment.
תככא דשיראי, Takhakh deshira, the thing that eats away at silk is
called
תככא. Takhakh. ואילא דענבי, Ve'ila de'invei, the thing that eats away at
grapes is called אילא. Ila.
ופיה Upeh or פה, Pa, I don't know, דתאיני dete'einei is the
thing that eats away at figs is this thing
called פיה. Peh. וההא דרמוני Vehaha derimonei and ההא Haha is the
thing that eats away at pomegranates. כולהו, Kulehu, all of these things,
סכנתא sakanta are a danger. You know, don't eat them, they if
you eat they are they are not good for your health besides
probably being not kosher. Okay so anyway these are various types of
either moths or worms or whatever they are. So now we have
a
story. ההוא תלמידה דהוה יתיב קמיה דרבי יוחנן, Hahu talmida d'hava yasiv
kamei d'Rabbi Yochanan, there was a student sitting in front of רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. הוה קאכיל תאיני, Hava k'achal te'einei, he was eating
figs. אמר ליה, Amar lei, רבי, Rebbi, קוצין יש בתאינים, kotzin yesh
bate'einim, he said, רבי, Rebbi, it seems like there's some thorns in
the figs, I'm there's something like a, you know, pokey, sharp, that's
in these figs. So what he was actually tasting was one of
these worms, okay, and it was poking him, so he thought it
was like a he thought it was like a little thorn. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, קטליה פיה לדין. katlei pa ledaden. So פיה, Peh,
which is the name of the worm in the figs, has now
killed this person. I don't know if that was a that's not
very reassuring but he basically was saying, you got to go get
you to a hospital now because this is a danger, this is
danger, you just eaten one of the worms of these figs. All
right and now to the next משנה. Mishnah המוציא קופת הרוכלין, Hamotzi
kuppat harochlin, more on various things you can take out. This is
the last משנה Mishnah of this פרק. perek. More, so if you
take out a box of fragrances. Basically they would have people that
would go around selling fragrances and they'd have little, you know, like
little compartments in the box, each one containing a different fragrance and
you took out this box and it had all these little tiny
little boxes in it of different fragrances. אף על פי שיש בה
מינים הרבה, Af al pi she'yesh bah minim harbei, even though it
has many different fragrances and many different boxes, אינו חייב אלא חטאת
אחת. eino chayav ela chattas achas. You're only חייב chayav one because
it's all one act of taking out. Okay תוספות Tosafos has a
question like it's so very obvious, I mean even if it's one
state of forgetfulness and you take something out, you know, two different
acts of taking out they all combine for one sin offering. Certainly
in one act. But anyway that's what the משנה Mishnah. is saying,
don't define that as multiple acts, it's all one taking out even
though each one by itself would have been an act if it
was taken out separately. זרוני גינה, Zeronei gina, if you take out
seeds used for planting in like a vegetable garden, פחות מכגרוגרת, pachos
mikogeris, it's less than a גרוגרת gogeris which is the amount of
food because here it's not a food, here it's a seeds to
be planted. How much? רבי יהודה בן בתירא אומר חמישה, Rabbi Yehuda
ben Beseira omer chamisha, five seeds is enough to be חייב. chayav.
זרע קישואין, Zera kishu'in, if it is a what do you call
it, a cucumber seed or gourd seed, שנים, shnayim, even two is
enough. זרע דילועין, Zera dilu'in, oh a דלעת dila'at is like a
gourd. If it's a gourd seed, שנים, shnayim, two. זרע פול המצרי,
Zera pul hamitzri, the Egyptian פול, pul, some type of a lentil
bean, שנים shnayim also two. So those even two is enough of
significance. Now חגב חי טהור כל שהוא. chagav chai tahor kolshehu. If
you have a kosher live grasshopper, even the smallest size. מת, Meis,
if it's a dead kosher grasshopper, well then it's just food so
then כגרוגרת, kegogeris, it goes by the size of food which is
the size of a pressed fig. ציפורת כרמים, Tzippores keramim, if you
have a ציפורת כרמים tzippores keramim which is a type of a
non-kosher grasshopper, presumably that would be in the vines, בין חי בין
מת, bein chai bein meis, whether alive or dead, כל שהוא kolshehu
goes by the smallest amount. So why there even if it's dead
the smallest
amount? שמתצינו לה לרפואה Shematznino lah l'refua because there it's not first
of all it's not food, it's not kosher, and number two because
you would use it for some other purpose, you would use it
for some health purpose, so even the smallest amount would therefore is
significant. What, why alive is it significant by both of these, we
don't know yet. רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbi Yehuda omer אף המוציא חגב
חי טמא כל שהוא, af hamotzi chagav chai tamei kolshehu, even a
non-kosher grasshopper that the smallest amount if it's alive is a כל
שהוא. kol shehu. Why? שמתצינו לקטן לשחוק בה Shematznino lekatan litzchok bah
because, you know, kids play with their little grasshoppers, so presumably that's
the reason for the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma also that says a
live grasshopper is a כל שהוא. So the question is why does
it matter alive versus why does it matter kosher versus non-kosher? Right,
if it's dead you could say well if it's kosher it's food.
If it's not kosher you have no use for it. This ציפורת
כרמים tzippores keramim maybe has a health use. But if it's alive
and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says כל שהוא for a kosher
one, presumably you don't eat them when they're alive, so presumably it's
to play with it, why is there a difference between a kosher
and a non-kosher? So we'll see this in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's
take a look.
How can you have a kosher grasshopper?
What? What do you mean? Various locusts and grasshoppers are kosher. Yeah,
I mean the תורה Torah has a whole says, you know, אשר
לו כרעים ממעל לרגליו. asher lo khara'im mima'al leraglav. We don't we
don't distinguish them. There are תימנים Teimanim or whatever that have a
מסורה mesorah which are the kosher
and
which are not.
Well, okay, let's take a look at how you would use it,
alright? And let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says.
Alright, so גמרא. Gemara רמיני. Ramini. זבוב וכל הדק כדי לזבך לראש
חרוב דברי רבי עקיבא. Zevuv vechol hadak kidei lezavcha lerosh charuv divrei
Rabbi Akiva. All of this is like similar to the thing we
asked before, given amounts when things are at different stages, and the
גמרא Gemara put them all together and asked this a few weeks
ago, but now we're looking at it in its local case. So
we say that when you're taking out manure or like thin sand
which is used as a type of fertilizer, in order to do,
to just fertilize even one little head of cabbage, של כרוב, shel
kruv, דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. חכמים אומרים כדי לזבך קרישא,
Chachamim omrim kidei lezavcha kreisha, a leek. So even one sort of
vegetable plant. So how come when you take out the seed, it
has to be five seeds or two seeds? When you take out
the manure, it's enough for the sake of even one plant? So
אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, הא דזריע הא דלא זריע. ha
d'zari'a ha d'la zari'a. There's a difference between once it's been planted
and before it's been planted. לפי שאין אדם טורח להוציא נימא אחת
לזריעה. lefi she'ein adam tore'ach lehotzi nima achat lezri'ah. You don't take
out one seed to plant. When you're going to plant, you don't
bother with one seed. You have two, five, something of a little
more significance. Once it's already planted and growing, then you'll go out
to fertilize even just one of the plants, okay? So same thing
like we said before about the dyes, it matters what stage it
is, whether it's enough to be of significance. זרע
קישואין, zera kishu'in, when it comes to cucumbers too, two seeds. תנו
רבנן המוציא גרעינים. tanu rabanan hamotzi gar'inim. If you're taking out seeds.
אם לנטייה, im lentiyah, if you're taking it out for the sake
of planting, שתים, shtayim, then two, like we said in our משנה.
mishna אם לאכילה, im lachilah, if you're going to eat the seeds,
כמלא פי חזיר, kemelo pi chazir, the amount that would go into
the mouth of a pig. וכמה מלא פי חזיר? vechama melo pi
chazir? How much goes into the mouth of a pig, fills it
up? אחת, achat, one. Which is pretty bizarre. One seed? So רש״י
Rashi says this specifically means a date, a date pit. But even
so, like one date pit fills out the, I don't know. No,
well that's what you, the חזיר chazir does, the pig does.
Because you take it out for animal food.
Yeah, לאכילה lachilah mean not human food, for animal food, okay? But
I don't know what חזיר. chazir. Also תוספות Tosafot makes another point.
If you look at
תוספות שראוי ליתן לו לחזיר,
Tosafot
sheraui
litein lo lechazir, תוספות פירוש שראוי ליתן לו בכוכבים או למכור אבל
ישראל אסור לגדל חזיר. Tosafot perush sheraui litein lo bechochavim o limkor
aval Yisrael assur legadel chazir. And not because just חזיר chazir is
not כשר. kosher. Actually you can actually make business off of non-כשר
kosher items. There's a question about you can't be מייחד meyached your
business with only non-כשר kosher things, but there's specific issues around חזירים
chazirim based on other גמרות, Gemarot, so even beyond just the fact
that they're not
כשר. kosher. How tiny is it? Yeah, I don't know what that
means. I mean we had all these משניות Mishnayot before about, you
know, fills the mouth of a camel, fills the mouth of a
goat, and here we're told that one pit fills the mouth of
a חזיר? chazir? So yeah, I mean maybe it just means,
maybe it doesn't literally fill the mouth, maybe it just means that
one is enough for it to chew on and for it to
be happy with, like, you know, one stick of chewing gum type
of a thing. But still, that makes us rethink what this phrase
filling the mouth of really means, yes.
And what are Jews doing feeding pigs?
Well, I just told the תוספות, Tosafot, he says that you would,
it would be enough to sell to a non-Jew who wants to
feed his pig or something, okay? Or yeah.
What with the seeds? This is שבת, Shabbat, right? Yeah, so you
can't...
I know, I keep on saying this, it's not what you can
do on שבת. Shabbat. It's what would have significance in another context.
If I took out one cigarette or one match, that's an object
of significance, even if I can't use it today, okay? But I
took out something of minimum size to have some significance, right? If
I took, if I took out a dollar bill, that's something of
significance, even if I can't use it today, so that, so it
doesn't matter whether you can do it on שבת Shabbat or not.
Okay, alright. Anyway, so it says, okay. אם להסיק, im lehasik, if
you're doing it for firewood, כדי לבשל ביצה קלה, kidei levashel beitzah
kalah,
enough to cook again this light egg. אם לחשבון, im lecheshbon, if
you're doing it in order for like to use it as counting.
You know, sometimes they would use them as markers, so that you
would, you know, so you'd use these pits for, you know, for
like a, what's it called? An abacus?
Or some type of a way you use them as counting markers.
Then שתים, shtayim, two. אחרים אומרים חמש, acherim omrim chamesh, others say
five. What is the idea of two or five? I'll read you
this רש״י, Rashi, I didn't exactly understand it. רש״י Rashi says, אומרים
ה, omrim hei, it's about 15 lines down. He says דעד ארבעה
גלולות חשיב אינש ולא מנשי, d'ad arba'ah glulot chashiv inash velo minshei,
until four you remember and don't forget, ואין צריך להשיא סימן אבל
חמש מנשי ומוסיף סימן לכולהו. ve'ein tzarich lehassi siman aval chamesh minshei
umosif siman lechulehu. When you get up to five, then you forget
the number and you have to give a סימן. siman. I'm not
sure...
Actually seven I think, which is why phone numbers were seven digits.
Yeah, but I don't understand why, if, but you're not remembering distinct
digits. He's saying you have five stones that you're using as some
type of a marker or memory aid, and you don't need less
than, four stones you don't need, but five stones, I'm not exactly
clear to me how they're using these stones.
There's generally a limit you can look at and eyeball and go
four. That
was—I read a book about origin of mathematics and numbers and counting
and that
once you pass four then it gets harder
to visually see and you have to have a method of counting.
Right, but then wouldn't you want, but then you would, but then
if you were being logical about it, you would have—you would—the number
of counters would be the numbers more than four. Yeah, that. Why
isn't it five counters if up until then I can—I don't know,
anyway, whatever. Okay, so
okay, תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan המוציא שני נימין hamotzi shnei nimim if
you take out two hairs
מזנב הסוס ומזנב הפרה miznav hasus umiznav hapara from a horse hair
or from a cow hair חייב chayav שמתקינה לנשבין shematkinah lenishvin because
you put it aside to use for types of traps, like I
don't know, a bird trap or something like the hair trigger, you
know, so it was a snare. So anyway, so even two is
significant. Now, מכשא של חזיר michsha shel chazir if you take a
pig hair, which is harder, which is called, you know, which is
like stiffer, אחת achat even one. Rashi says you use it somehow
to put on top of some stitching. ציפורת כרמים Tziporet kramim צורי
דקלא tzurei dikla ושניים ushnayim if you take a type of a
what do you call it? Like a palm tree, a frond, or
not a frond, but some type of a part of the vine
of the palm around the palm, then it's two because you would
use them as what do you call those things when you like
make wicker baskets, you know, and so anyway, those are the types
of things since you would use them in a weaving process, two
is significant. And if it is תורי דקלא turei dikla which is
more of a thinner vine type of a thing around the around
the palm tree אחת achat just one. Rashi says ולא ידעתי למאי
חזי velo yadati lemah chazi I don't know what you'd use it
for. Okay, anyway. Now ציפורת כרמים Tziporet kramim moving on, so this
ציפורת כרמים Tziporet kramim this thing of the vines is used for
רפואה. refuah. So מאי ציפורת כרמים mai Tziporet kramim what is a
ציפורת כרמים? tziporet kramim? So אמר רב Rav, אמר רב Rav פלייא
בירי. palya be’eri. So Rashi says just that's just the name. I
don't know, do they give a translation for it in your various
English translations? It says it's some kind of a locust. Some type
of a locust. Okay. אמר אביי amar Abaye ומשתכח בדיקלא דחד נבארא.
umishtakach bedikla dechad nevara. It is found in a in a palm
tree of it is like of one vine, meaning that it's that
it's very young and has not yet had these sort of the
various you know leaves and vines wrap around it. ועביד לה v’avid
lah and now we get to find out what they would use
it for לחכמה lechuchmah in order to be wise. So here's how
you would do it. אכיל ליה לפלגא דימינא. achil leh lepalga deyamina.
You eat the half of the right half. I don't know what
the right half means, I mean what way is it facing you
that you know the right half of the left half, maybe you
split it down lengthwise rather than widthwise. I don't know, anyway, you
eat the right half. ופלגא דשמאלא רמי ליה בגיפסתא upalga desmala rami
leh begifsta and the left half you put into some type of
a tube, okay, דנחשא denachsha made out of metal of copper, copper
tube. וחתים ליה בשיתין גושפנקי vechatim leh beshitin gushpanki you seal it
with 60 seals, Rashi says not literally 60 seals, but you put
a seal seals on this on this copper tube. ותלי ליה באברא
דשמאלא vetali leh be’ebra desmala you suspend it by your on your
left arm. וסימנך vesimanach and the way to remember that you eat
the right part and you suspend the left part on your arm,
לב חכם לימינו ולב כסיל לשמאלו lev chacham limino velev ksil lismolo
you want to be smart and so the pasuk says the the
heart of the wise person is on his right and the heart
of the foolish is on his left, so you eat the right
half of it. וחכים כמה דבעי vechakim kama deba’ei you learn as
much as you want because now it would be very easy for
you to learn. This was before they had caffeine or whatever, I
don't know. So now it would be very easy for you to
learn, so you learn all the information you want to learn. וגמר
כמה דבעי vegamir kama deba’ei and you know you you master everything
you want to learn. ואכיל ליה לאידך פלגא. ve’achil leh le’idach palga.
And then you eat the other half and then you solidify all
of your learning. דאי לאו de’ilavo because if you don't do that
you throw away the other half, then מעקר תלמודו me’akar talmudo everything
you learned will get will disappear, so it'll be a waste. So
you have to after you've finished learning you eat the other half.
Now—wait, so they pass some locust down here? Exactly. Now again, maybe
I think when I read the Mishna I said it was non-kosher,
but maybe again, maybe this is assuming that it is kosher. Or
maybe it's considered medicine? It doesn't need to be kosher? That's not
so clear, especially here where it's not even for a sickness or
whatever. I mean you can't have—I mean it depends if it's ראוי
לאכילה ra’ui la’achila not ראוי לאכילה ra’ui la’achila and so anyway, so
could—probably it's assuming that it is kosher. For the non-kosher we turn
to the last part here. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer, אף
המוציא. Rabbi Yehuda says even if it's a live non-kosher locust, it's
a kosher because kids play with it. So the Gemara says ותנא
קמא סבר לא. veTanna Kamma savar lo. And Tanna Kamma says no,
if it's not kosher, then it's not significant. Kids don't play with
it. Yeah, but the מתניתא matnita spoke about רפואה refuah about ציפורת
כרמים. Tziporet kramim. And here they're saying what it's used for. So
is this—is this something different? No— The רפואה refuah is to be
smart. Right. But then how come... So I'm just saying I don't
know if it's kosher or not. Maybe it's a kosher locust. I
don't know whether it's assumed it's kosher. But apparently like a רפואה
refuah isn't necessarily for an ailment, this is for just... Yeah, so
right רפואה refuah here doesn't mean for an ailment, but again, that's
not that you can use that term at other places where we
say רפואה. refuah. You're just saying it has a Shabbos use, some
type of a benefit. Right. Okay. רפואה refuah here being used loosely,
not to have given it that status necessarily for other areas. Okay.
So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma savar lo, that no, if it's
not kosher, kids don't play with it. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? You
wouldn't want your kid to play with a non-kosher locust, דילמא אכלי,
dilma achlei, maybe he'll eat it. Okay, non-kosher. So the גמרא Gemara
says אי הכי צור נמי, ei hachi tzor nami, so even if
it's kosher, maybe he'll eat it while it's alive? Why would that
be a problem? Not because it's אבר מן החי, ever min hachai,
because locusts don't require שחיטה, shechitah, so it's not a problem of
כשרות kashrut eating it while it's alive, but here is what the
problem is. The problem is... דהוה רב כהנא הוה קאי קמיה דרב,
de-hava Rav Kahana hava kai kamei de-Rav, רב כהנא Rav Kahana was
in front of רב, והוה קא מעבר שושיבא אפומיה, ve-hava ka ma'avir
shushiva apumei, and a שושיבא shushiva which was some type of a
non-kosher locust was flying around his mouth as he was talking. אמר
ליה, amar lei, and רב said to him, שקליה, shaklei, you get
it away from me. Like why? דלא לימרו מיכל קא אכיל, de-lo
limru meichal ka achal, people will see your mouth, you're talking and
it's going, it's right near your mouth, maybe it'll even go in
your mouth, and people will say you're eating it. Now why is
that a problem? It was a kosher locust. Because וקעבר משום בל
תשקצו את נפשתיכם, ve-ka'avar mishum bal teshaktzu et nafshoteichem, because it's a
prohibition of do not make yourself disgusting, meaning don't, so even if
it's not, even if it's kosher, it's disgusting to eat a live
thing. And therefore, whether it literally means you transgress or it's like
a, you know, it's sort of it's against the point of that
פסוק pasuk exactly, whether it's a technical transgression exactly what the parameters
of that לאו lav are, but nevertheless, you should not be doing
that. That's a disgusting thing. So why would, so you wouldn't want
your kid playing with a live locust, even kosher, he'll eat it
and it's בל תשקצו, bal teshaktzu, it'll be this prohibition. אלא דילמא
מית ואכלי. ella dilma mayis ve-achlei. Fine. The concern is that fine,
the kid won't eat it when it's alive. He knows not to
eat his live pets. The concern is that it'll die and he'll
eat it. So you let him play with a kosher locust, if
it dies he'll eat it. But you don't let him play with
a non-kosher locust because if it dies, you don't want him to
eat it if it dies. So therefore non-kosher locusts don't have any
value, you don't let your kids play with it. So רב יהודה,
Rav Yehuda, why would רב יהודה Rav Yehuda let his kid play
with a non-kosher locust? Because he said אי מית, ei mayis, if
it dies, קטן מספד ספיד ליה, katan mispad safid lei, he's not
going to eat it, he'll have a little funeral for it. So
יספוד, yispod, he'll eulogize. So therefore I don't have to be concerned
that my kids will eat their dead pets. So therefore because of
that I let my kid play with a non-kosher locust and therefore
a non-kosher locust if it's alive has significance because it's something I
would bring home for my kid as a pet. Yeah, follow that
logic. Kids, you know, buried our pet hamsters. Right, right, so that's
what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is saying. So that's exactly what he's
saying, you'll have a little funeral for it. My mind blown that
kids did the same thing 2000 years ago. Yes, strange because, right,
because of the generally we're assigning standards to all these things and
so it's this
idea that רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda says well my kids are different. Well I said my
kids are to be a little funny, but he would say kids
would, you would let your kid, I'm sorry, I was just being,
trying to be a little cute, but he wasn't saying my kid,
but he would say, look, I think you would let kids play
with it because you wouldn't be concerned that they would eat it.
And the חכמים Chachamim say no you wouldn't. So again, but that's
also becomes a funny question, like why don't we see what's done
out there? Do parents let their kids play with these locusts or
do they not let them play with their locusts? Now I do
want to point out to you a very interesting רש"י Rashi which
has significance about letting your kid play with it. If you take
a look at רש"י, Rashi he says דילמא אכל, dilma achal, it's
like right across from where it says ויקרא י"א Vayikra Yud Aleph
in the margin between רש"י Rashi and the גמרא. Gemara He says
ואפילו למאן דאמר קטן אוכל נבילות אין בית דין מצווין עליו להפרישו.
ve-afilu le-man de-amar katan ochel nevelot ein Beit Din metzuvin alav le-hafrisho.
Big deal if your kid eats it and it's not kosher. There's
an opinion that says that if a minor is eating non-kosher food,
the בית דין, Beit Din, meaning the community, has no responsibility to
stop him from doing it. He's only a minor. Now one answer
would have been to this question, yes, but you're his father or
his mother and therefore you have a heightened responsibility to חינוך chinuch
to prevent that even if it's not because of the איסור issur
but at least a general חינוך chinuch responsibility. But let's see what
רש"י Rashi says why it's a concern that he'll do it. רש"י
Rashi says מודה הוא דלא יהבינן ליה בידיים. modeh hu de-lo yavinan
lei be-yadayim. He would agree that you don't actually directly feed them
non-kosher. דתניא לא תאכלום לא תאכילום להזהיר גדולים על הקטנים. de-tanya lo
tochlum lo tachilum le-hazhir gedolim al haktanim. Now the problem here is
you're not feeding him this locust. You're giving him a locust to
play with. But a concern is that he'll come to eat the
locust and רש"י Rashi calls that as if you're feeding him בידיים.
be-yadayim. So the נודע ביהודה Noda Biyehuda has a very fascinating תשובה
teshuvah about a parent that had to put their kid in an
institution and it was, I forget whether it was because of mental
illness or whatever the case was, and it was non-kosher food. And
were they prohibited in doing so because it's like מאכיל בידיים? ma'achil
be-yadayim? by directly feeding their kid טרייף. traif. Not directly feeding their
kid טרייף, traif, they're sending him to this institution where he has
to be sent and other people are going to feed him טרייף,
traif, but they're putting him in that scenario where that's necessarily going
to happen. And רש"י here calls that you giving your kid this
little, you know, sort of locust to play with when you're giving
it to them, it's alive. But if it'll likely lead to it
dying and him eating it, he calls it מאכיל בידיים, ma'achil be'yadayim,
you know, as if you're directly feeding. So it does raise these
really important questions about those, that's a longer discussion. Okay, but... I
know, now, now I whet your... Oh, maybe you're right, maybe it
was the חתם סופר. Chasam Sofer. I thought it was... maybe you're
right, maybe it was the חתם סופר. Chasam Sofer. Okay, I have
to... I didn't check it out in time, but I remember that
there was a תשובה teshuva about this and about the parameters of
about מאכיל בידיים, ma'achil be'yadayim, and this רש"י is interesting in that
context. So yeah, did you say you want to say something? I
was just wondering the timing between the חתם סופר Chasam Sofer and
these hospitals, because these institutions like that didn't exist until... Right, so
the חתם סופר Chasam Sofer is 19th century or late, very late
18... early 19th century. Right, right, right. So, yeah, so Seth is
probably right. Okay, so הדרן עלך אמר רבי עקיבא. Hadran Alach Amar
Rabbi Akiva. Now we start the next פרק, perek, which is about,
any guesses? Carrying. ממדברת הוצאה. Mi'midbarat hotza'ah. There you go. I'm not
kidding. So, okay, thankfully it will switch topics in the middle. Okay?
We are pretty... let me just check. Yes, yes, in about two
or three more pages we are going to finally switch away from
carrying to other types of מלאכות. melachos. But maybe four pages. Anyway,
המצניע. Ha'matznia. So, if you, now remember, all of these minimum sizes,
when we started the minimum sizes, it was all about if you
do not specifically set it aside for that purpose. But if you
do set some... but if you set something aside to give it
significance, you just carry something out randomly. But if you've set it
aside because this is
a minimum, this is a mount
that you want to do something with, then even the smallest amount
has significance and you have given it subjective significance. So that's what
this משנה mishna
turns to, that you've actually set it aside.
המצניע לזרע ולדוגמא ולרפואה. Ha'matznia le'zera u'li'dugma u'li'refuah. If you set something
aside either to plant or to use as a sample or for
health purposes, והוציאו בשבת חייב בכל שהוא. ve'hotzio be'shabbos chayav be'chol she'hu.
And then you took it out, you're חייב chayav even the smallest
amount, cause you have set aside something that for you has significance.
וכל אדם, Ve'chol adam, but a normal person, אינו חייב עליו אלא
כשיעורו, eino chayav alav ela ki'shiuro, is not חייב chayav even presumably
if he takes your thing out, even though you've given it significance,
for him he's only חייב chayav if he takes out the minimum
amount that we've been discussing until now.
Now, חזר והכניסו, chazar ve'hichniso, let's say you took out this, I
don't know, seed, with this one seed you were going to plant
a single
seed, and you had set
it aside for planting
and you took it out to the garden. And then you changed
your mind and
you brought it back into the house. So in that case, אינו
חייב אלא כשיעורו, eino chayav ela ki'shiuro, you're
not חייב chayav for the one seed. Cause the reason the seed
had significance was the combination that you gave it subjective significance and
you were taking it out for that purpose. Right? But if you
actually were bringing it back, essentially you're saying, "Forget it, I'm not
going to plant it," that undermines the significance you've given it and
therefore it would not go by the subjective significance, it would go
by the standard minimum amount. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara's
says on this. למה לי למתני המצניע? Lama li le'masni ha'matznia? Why
does it have to say "the המצניע"?
matznia ליתני המוציא לזרע ולדוגמא
ולרפואה.
Leisni ha'motzi le'zera
u'li'dugma u'li'refuah.
Why does it have to say "if you set aside"? It should
have said that if you took it out for those purposes, חייב
בכל שהוא. chayav be'chol she'hu. Now, that's a... the very fact the
גמרא Gemara's makes that assumption is a surprise, right? Because what you
normally would have said, like to give things real subjective weight, you
have to set it aside and give it significance. The גמרא Gemara
is assuming that you know what? That's not true. If I take
one seed out with the intent to plant it, that act of
taking it out with the intent to plant it is saying, "I
am giving this one seed significance." So even if I didn't set
it aside before, the fact that I took it out with that
intent gives it significance, which of course then raises the question, then
every case is that, right? Every case, if I take out seeds,
let's take what we just said before, like five types of vegetable
seeds, right? So as long as I'm taking it out for the
sake of planting it, why is it five? It should be one.
The גמרא says it's even without setting aside, just the act of
taking it out with that in mind gives it weight. So according
to this, you know what? All the stuff we talked before was
when you were taking it out without any particular plant to use
it, just to move it from one place to another. Like I
wanted to bring over my vegetable seeds to your house. In that
case, it goes by five vegetable seeds. But if I want to
bring out my vegetable seeds to plant, so then it's even one.
So all of a sudden it's no longer about even being המצניע,
matznia, setting aside ahead of time. As long as you're taking it
out to use it and your intent is to use it, even
the smallest amount is חייב. chayav. So why do we have to
give the example of המצניע? matznia? Specifically setting aside or in your
mind? No, so that's what it's doing. It's shifting. We thought the
משנה was physically setting aside. The גמרא is now saying you don't
even need that. As long as you take it out to use,
even the smallest amount is חייב. chayav. Okay, so all the cases
until... So now that that's a minimum amount is when you weren't
taking them out to be used, you were just taking them out
to transport them. But if you were actually taking them out for
the sake of using it, there would be no minimum size. That's
the גמרא assertion, which is pretty radical. Until now it's been this
idea of מצניע, matznia, but the גמרא shifted it to anytime you
take it out to use is the there's no minimum. Yes. Is
this the part we're talking about שבת? Shabbat? Yes. So even I
know you said before, even if you can't use it on שבת,
Shabbat, but who would take it out to plant? The same guy
who would take it out without an עירוב. eruv. Okay, so אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, so said אביי, Abaye, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bemai
askinan, what are we talking about? כגון שהצניעו, kegon she-hitznio, you set
aside this one seed, ושכח למה הצניעו, veshachach lama hitznio, and you
forgot why you set it aside. והשתא קא מפיק ליה סתמא, ve-hashta
ka mafik lei stama, and now you're taking it out not to
plant but just to like bring it over to your friend or
something. Okay, so in the act of taking it out, you're not
giving it special significance because you're not taking it out to plant.
But its significance comes from the fact that you had set it
aside prior and therefore even though you didn't remember why, that gave
it significance. מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought בטולי בטליה
מחשבתו bitulei batlei machshavto that you are negating this earlier sort of
act that you did of setting it aside because now you're not
you don't remember why. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, כל העושה
על דעת ראשונה הוא עושה. kol ha-oseh al da'at rishonah hu oseh.
So it teaches you no, what you're doing now is defined by
your original intent. Since originally you gave one seed significance and you
set it aside, even though now you're doing it a little bit
oblivious, it's defined by that original thing and it still has significance.
But the bigger חידוש chiddush now is you don't even need the
act of מצניע. matznia. So let me just point out to you
the implications and with this we'll end. We said before if you
remember like it spoke about if you're taking out where was it?
המוציא גרעינין. hamotzi gar'inin. If it's for planting, two. If it's for
eating, פי חזיר. pi chazir. If it's for if it's for burning,
ביצת קלה. beitzat kallah. So תוספות Tosafot says I don't understand. As
long as you're taking it out with a specific intent in mind,
it should be חייב, chayav, right? That's what we said. If you
take it out with an intent to use it. So what do
you mean if it's for planting, two, if it's for eating, you
know, the pig, if it's for burning in order to make firewood
for an egg? If you're taking it out to do something with
it, it's even a כל שהוא. So תוספות Tosafot says you have
to interpret all of those things, not what's in your mind, but
what sort of that type of wood is generally used for. Meaning
if it's the type of seeds that are used for planting, it's
two. If it's the type that's used for feeding pigs, this. If
it's the type that's used for burning. But as soon as you
have a specific intent in mind, this גמרא is saying that even
the smallest amount because now you've
given it significance
because
you're taking it out to use even in this
small size. Okay, and we'll end with that today. Alright. No locusts.
Okay. No locusts in this any of those? Good night. No.